<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-shielding-intro">
 <title>Introduction</title>
 <info xmlns:d="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"><revhistory xml:id="rh-cha-shielding-intro">
   <revision>
     <date>2021-07-27</date>
     <revdescription>
       <para/>
     </revdescription>
   </revision>
 </revhistory>
</info>
 <para>
  In the Linux kernel, the cpuset facility provides a mechanism for creating
  logical entities called <quote>cpusets</quote> that encompass definitions
  of CPUs and NUMA Memory Nodes (if NUMA is available). Cpusets constrain
  the CPU and Memory placement of a task to only the resources defined
  within that cpuset. These cpusets can then be arranged into a nested
  hierarchy visible in the <quote>cpuset</quote> virtual file system. Sets
  of tasks can be assigned to these cpusets to constrain the resources that
  they use. The tasks can be moved from one cpuset to another to use
  other resources defined in those other cpusets.
 </para>
 <para>
  The <command>cset</command> command is a Python application that provides
  a command line front-end for the Linux cpusets functionality. Working with
  cpusets directly can be confusing and slightly complex. The cset tool
  hides that complexity behind an easy-to-use command line interface.
 </para>
 <para>
  There are two distinct use cases for cset: the basic shielding use case
  and the <quote>advanced</quote> case of using raw <command>set</command>
  and <command>proc</command> subcommands. The basic shielding function is
  accessed with the <command>shield</command> subcommand and described in
  the next section. Using the raw <command>set</command> and
  <command>proc</command> subcommands allows one to set up arbitrarily
  complex cpusets and is described in
  <xref linkend="cha-shielding-cpuset"/>.
 </para>
 <para>
  Note that in general, one either uses the <command>shield</command>
  subcommand or a combination of the <command>set</command> and
  <command>proc</command> subcommands. One rarely, if ever, uses all of
  these subcommands together. Doing so will likely become too confusing.
  Additionally, the <command>shield</command> subcommand sets up its
  required cpusets with exclusively marked CPUs. This can interfere with
  your cpuset strategy. If you find that you need more functionality for
  your strategy than <command>shield</command> provides, go ahead and
  transition to using <command>set</command> and <command>proc</command>
  exclusively. It is straightforward to implement what
  <command>shield</command> does with a few extra <command>set</command> and
  <command>proc</command> subcommands.
 </para>
 <variablelist>
  <title>Obtaining online help</title>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>For a full list of cset subcommands</term>
   <listitem>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> <option>help</option></screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>For in-depth help on individual subcommands</term>
   <listitem>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> <option>help</option> <replaceable>&lt;subcommand&gt;</replaceable></screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>For options on individual subcommands</term>
   <listitem>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> <replaceable>&lt;subcommand&gt;</replaceable> <option>(-h | --help)</option></screen>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
</chapter>
