<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="cha-shielding-cpuset">
 <title>Full-featured cpuset manipulation commands</title>
 <para>
  While basic shielding as described above is useful and a common use model
  for <command>cset</command>, there comes a time when more functionality
  will be desired to implement your strategy. To implement this,
  <command>cset</command> provides two subcommands: <command>set</command>,
  which allows you to manipulate cpusets; and <command>proc</command>, which
  allows you to manipulate processes within those cpusets.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-set">
  <title>The set subcommand</title>

  <para>
   To do anything with cpusets, you must be able to create, adjust,
   rename, move, and destroy them. The <command>set</command> subcommand
   allows the management of cpusets in such a manner.
  </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-set-create-destroy">
   <title>Creating and destroying cpusets with <command>set</command></title>
   <para>
    The basic syntax of <command>set</command> for cpuset creation is:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1-3 -s my_cpuset1
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "my_cpuset1"</screen>
   <para>
    This creates a cpuset named <literal>my_cpuset1</literal> with a CPUSPEC
    of CPU1, CPU2 and CPU3. The CPUSPEC is the same concept as described in
    the <xref linkend="sec-shielding-model-ex-setup-teardown"/>. The
    <command>set</command> subcommand also takes a <option>-m</option>/<option>--mem</option>
    option that lets you specify the memory nodes the <command>set</command>
    will use and flags to make the CPUs and MEMs exclusive to the
    cpuset. If you are on a non-NUMA machine, leave the
    <option>-m</option> option out and the default memory node
    <literal>0</literal> will be used.
   </para>
   <para>
    Like with <command>shield</command>, you can adjust the CPUs and
    MEMs with subsequent calls to set. If, for example, you want to adjust
    the <literal>my_cpuset1</literal> cpuset to only use CPUs 1 and 3 (and
    omit CPU2), then issue the following command.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1,3 -s my_cpuset1
cset: --&gt; modified cpuset "my_cpuset</screen>
   <para>
    <command>cset</command> will then adjust the CPUs that are assigned to
    the <literal>my_cpuset1</literal> set to only use CPU1 and CPU3.
   </para>
   <para>
    To rename a cpuset, use the <option>-n/--newname</option> option. For
    example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -s my_cpuset1 -n super_set
cset: --&gt; renaming "/cpusets/my_cpuset1" to "super_set"</screen>
   <para>
    Renames the cpuset called <literal>my_cpuset1</literal> to
    <literal>super_set</literal>.
   </para>
   <para>
    To destroy a cpuset, use the <option>-d/--destroy</option> option as
    follows.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -d super_set
cset: --&gt; processing cpuset "super_set", moving 0 tasks to parent "/"...
cset: --&gt; deleting cpuset "/super_set"
cset: done</screen>
   <para>
    This command destroys the newly created cpuset called
    <literal>super_set</literal>. When a cpuset is destroyed, all the tasks
    running in it are moved to the parent cpuset. The root cpuset, which
    always exists and always contains all CPUs, cannot be destroyed. You may
    also give the <option>--destroy</option> option a list of cpusets to
    destroy.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Information about the mounted cpuset file system</title>
    <para>
     The <command>cset</command> subcommand creates the cpusets based on a
     mounted cpuset file system. You do not need to know where that file
     system is mounted, although it is easy to figure out (by default it is
     on <filename>/cpusets</filename>). When you give the
     <command>set</command> subcommand a name for a new cpuset, it is
     created wherever the cpuset file system is mounted.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    To create a cpuset hierarchy, then you must give a path to
    the <command>cset set</command> subcommand. This path will always begin
    with the root cpuset, for which the path is <filename>/</filename>. For
    example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1,3 -s top_set
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "top_set"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 3 -s /top_set/sub_set
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "/top_set/sub_set"</screen>
   <para>
    These commands created two cpusets: <literal>top_set</literal> and
    <literal>sub_set</literal>. The <literal>top_set</literal> uses CPU1 and
    CPU3. It has a subset of <literal>sub_set</literal> which only uses
    CPU3. Once you have created a subset with a path, then if the name is
    unique, you do not need to specify the path to affect it. If
    the name is not unique, then <command>cset</command> will complain and
    ask you to use the path. For example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1,3 -s sub_set
cset: --&gt; modified cpuset "sub_set</screen>
   <para>
    This command adds CPU1 to the <literal>sub_set</literal> cpuset for its
    use. Note that using the path in this case is optional.
   </para>
   <para>
    If you attempt to destroy a cpuset which has sub-cpusets,
    <command>cset</command> will complain and not do it unless you use the
    <option>-r/--recurse</option> and the <option>--force</option> options.
    If you do use <option>--force</option>, then all the tasks running in
    all subsets of the deletion target cpuset will be moved to the
    target’s parent cpuset and all cpusets.
   </para>
   <para>
    Moving a cpuset from under a certain cpuset to a different location is
    not implemented.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-set-list">
   <title>Listing cpusets with set</title>
   <para>
    To list cpusets, use the <command>set</command> subcommand with the
    <option>-l/--list</option> option. For example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       320   1    /
one          3 n          0 n       0     1    /one</screen>
   <para>
    This shows that there is currently one cpuset present called
    <literal>one</literal>. (Of course there is also the
    <literal>root</literal> set, which is always present.) The output shows
    that the one cpuset has no tasks running in it. The
    <literal>root</literal> cpuset has 320 tasks running. The
    <option>-X</option> for CPUs and MEMs fields denotes whether the CPUs
    and MEMs in the cpusets are marked exclusive to those cpusets. Note that
    the <literal>one</literal> cpuset has subsets as indicated by a
    <literal>1</literal> in the <literal>Subs</literal> field. You can
    specify a cpuset to list with the <command>set</command> subcommand as
    follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -s one
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
one          3 n          0 n       0     1   /one
two          3 n          0 n       0     1   /one/two</screen>
   <para>
    This output shows that there is a cpuset called <literal>two</literal>
    in cpuset <literal>one</literal> and it also has subset. You can also
    ask for a recursive listing as follows:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -r
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       320   1    /
one          3 n          0 n       0     1    /one
two          3 n          0 n       0     1    /one/two
three        3 n          0 n       0     0    /one/two/three</screen>
   <para>
    This command lists all cpusets existing on the system since it asks for
    a recursive listing beginning at the <literal>root</literal> cpuset.
    Incidentally, should you need to specify the <literal>root</literal>
    cpuset you can use either <filename>root</filename> or
    <filename>/</filename> to specify it explicitly—just remember that the
    <literal>root</literal> cpuset cannot be deleted or modified.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc">
  <title>The <command>proc</command> subcommand</title>

  <para>
   Now that you know how to create, rename and destroy cpusets with the
   <command>set</command> subcommand, the next step is to manage threads and
   processes in those cpusets. The subcommand to do this is called
   <command>proc</command> and it allows you to execute processes into a
   cpuset, move existing tasks around existing cpusets, and list tasks
   running in specified cpusets. For the following examples, let us assume a
   cpuset setup of two sets as follows:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       309   2    /
two          2 n          0 n       3     0    /two
three        3 n          0 n       10    0    /three</screen>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-list">
   <title>Listing tasks with <command>proc</command></title>
   <para>
    Operation of the <command>proc</command> subcommand follows the same
    model as the <command>set</command> subcommand. For example, to list
    tasks in a cpuset, you need to use the <option>-l/--list</option> option
    and specify the cpuset by name or, if the name exists multiple times in
    the cpuset hierarchy, by path. For example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 3 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root     16141 4300  Soth bash
root     16171 16141 Soth bash
root     16703 16171 Roth python ./cset proc -l two</screen>
   <para>
    This output shows us that the cpuset called two has CPU2 only attached
    to it and is running three tasks: two shells and the
    <command>python</command> command to list it. Note that cpusets are
    inherited so that if a process is contained in a cpuset, then any
    children it spawns also run within that set. In this case, the
    <command>python</command> command to list set <literal>two</literal> was
    run from a shell already running in set <literal>two</literal>. This can
    be seen by the PPID (parent process ID) of the <command>python</command>
    command matching the PID of the shell.
   </para>
   <para>
    Additionally, the <literal>SPPr</literal> field needs explanation. SPPr
    stands for <literal>State, Policy and Priority</literal>. You can see
    that the initial two tasks are stopped and running in timeshare
    priority, marked as <literal>oth</literal> (for
    <literal>other</literal>). The last task is marked as running,
    <literal>R</literal> and at timeshare priority,
    <literal>oth</literal>. If any of these tasks would have been at real
    time priority, the policy would be shown as <literal>f</literal>
    for FIFO or <literal>r</literal> for round robin. The priority would
    be a number from 1 to 99. See below for an example.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s root | head -7
cset: "root" cpuset of CPUSPEC(0-3) with 309 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root        1     0 Soth init [5]
root        2     0 Soth [kthreadd]
root        3     2 Sf99 [migration/0]
root        4     2 Sf99 [posix_cpu_timer]</screen>
   <para>
    This output shows the first few tasks in the <literal>root</literal>
    cpuset. Note that both <literal> init</literal> and
    <literal>[kthread]</literal> are running at timeshare; however, the
    <literal>[migration/0]</literal> and
    <literal>[posix_cpu_timer]</literal> kernel threads are running at
    real-time policy of FIFO and priority of <literal>99</literal>.
    Incidentally, this output is from a system running the real-time Linux
    kernel which runs some kernel threads at real-time priorities. And
    finally, note that you can use <command>cset</command> as any other
    Linux tool and include it in pipelines as in the example above.
   </para>
   <para>
    Taking a peek into the third cpuset called <literal>three</literal>, you
    can see output such as:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s three
cset: "three" cpuset of CPUSPEC(3) with 10 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
&exampleuser;      16165     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16169     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16170     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16237     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16491     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16492     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16493     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      17243     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      17244     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      17265     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...</screen>
   <para>
    This output shows that a lot of <literal>beagled</literal> tasks are
    running in this cpuset and it also shows an ellipsis
    (<literal>…</literal>) at the end of their listings. If you see this
    ellipsis, that means that the command was too long to fit onto an 80
    character screen. To see the entire command line, use the
    <option>-v/--verbose</option> flag:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s three -v | head -4
cset: "three" cpuset of CPUSPEC(3) with 10 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
&exampleuser;      16165     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg --autostarted --indexing-delay 300</screen>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-exec">
   <title>Execing tasks with <literal>proc</literal></title>
   <para>
    To execute a task into a cpuset, the <command>proc</command> subcommand
    needs to be employed with the <option>-e/--exec</option> option. Let us
    execute a shell into the cpuset named <literal>two</literal> in our set.
    First, check to see what is running that set:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 0 tasks running

&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -s two -e bash
cset: --&gt; last message, executed args into cpuset "/two", new pid is: 20955

&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 2 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root     20955 19253 Soth bash
root     20981 20955 Roth python ./cset proc -l two</screen>
   <para>
    You can see that initially, <literal>two</literal> had nothing running
    in it. After the completion of the second command, list
    <literal>two</literal> again and see that there are two tasks running:
    the shell which you executed and the <command>python cset</command> command
    that is listing the cpuset. The reason for the second task is that the
    cpuset property of a running task is inherited by all its children.
    Because you executed the listing command from the new shell which was bound
    to cpuset two, the resulting process for the listing is also bound to
    cpuset <literal>two</literal>. Let us test that by running a new
    shell with no prefixed <command>cset</command> command.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>bash</command>


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 3 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root     20955 19253 Soth bash
root     21118 20955 Soth bash
root     21147 21118 Roth python ./cset proc -l two</screen>
   <para>
    Here again, you can see that the second shell, PID <literal>21118</literal>,
    has a parent PID of <literal>20955</literal> which is the first shell.
    Both shells, and the listing command, are running in the two cpuset.
   </para>
   <note>
    <title>Separating the Tool Options From the cset Command</title>
    <para>
     <command>cset</command> follows the tradition of separating the tool
     options from the command to be executed options with a double hyphen
     (<literal>--</literal>). This is not shown in this simple example, but
     if the command you want to execute also takes options, separate them with
     the double hyphen as follows:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -s myset -e mycommand -- -v</screen>
    <para>
     The <option>-v</option> will be passed to
     <replaceable>mycommand</replaceable>, and not to <option>cset</option>.
    </para>
   </note>
   <tip>
    <title>Executing a shell into a cpuset</title>
    <para>
     Executing a shell into a cpuset is a useful way to experiment with
     running tasks in that cpuset since all children of the shell will also
     run in the same cpuset.
    </para>
   </tip>
   <para>
    If you misspell the command to be
    executed, the result may be puzzling. For example:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -s two -e blah-blah
cset: --&gt; last message, executed args into cpuset "/two", new pid is: 21655
cset: **&gt; [Errno 2] No such file or directory</screen>
   <para>
    The result is no new process even though a new PID is output. The reason
    for the message is of course that the <command>cset</command> process
    forked in preparation of the execution, but the command
    <command>blah-blah</command> was not found to execute it.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-move">
   <title>Moving tasks with <command>proc</command></title>
   <para>
    Although the ability to execute a task into a cpuset is fundamental, you
    will most likely be moving tasks between cpusets more often. Moving
    tasks is accomplished with the <option>-m/--move</option> and
    <option>-p/--pid</option> options to the <command>proc</command>
    subcommand of <command>cset</command>. The <option>move</option> option
    tells the <command>proc</command> subcommand that a task move is
    requested. The <option>-p/--pid</option> option takes an argument called
    a PIDSPEC (PID Specification). The PIDSPEC defines which tasks get
    operated on.
   </para>
   <para>
    The PIDSPEC can be a single process ID, a list of process IDs separated
    by commas, and a list of process ID ranges also separated by commas. For
    example:
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><option>--pid</option> 1234</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This PIDSPEC argument specifies that PID <literal>1234</literal> will be
       moved.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><option>--pid</option> 1234,42,1934,15000,15001,15002</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This PIDSPEC argument specifies that only listed tasks will be
       moved.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term><option>-p</option> 5000,5100,6010-7000,9232</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       This PIDSPEC argument specifies that tasks <literal>5000</literal>,
       <literal>5100</literal> and <literal>9232</literal> will be moved along
       with any existing task with PID in the range <literal>6010</literal>
       through <literal>7000</literal> inclusive.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
   <note>
    <title>Information about the range in a PIDSPEC</title>
    <para>
     A range in a PIDSPEC does not need to have running tasks for every
     number in that range. In fact, it is not even an error if there are no
     tasks running in that range; none will be moved in that case. The range
     simply specifies to act on any tasks that have a PID or TID that is
     within that range.
    </para>
   </note>
   <para>
    The following example moves the current shell into the cpuset
    named <literal>two</literal> with a range PIDSPEC and back out to the
    <literal>root</literal> cpuset with the Bash variable for the current
    PID.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 0 tasks running


&prompt.user;<command>echo</command> $$
19253


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -p 19250-19260 -t two
cset: moving following pidspec: 19253
cset: moving 1 userspace tasks to /two
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 2 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root     19253 16447 Roth bash
root     29456 19253 Roth python ./cset proc -l -s two


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -p $$ -t root
cset: moving following pidspec: 19253
cset: moving 1 userspace tasks to /
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 0 tasks running</screen>
   <para>
    Use of the appropriate PIDSPEC can thus be handy to move tasks and
    groups of tasks. Additionally, there is one more option that can help
    with multi-threaded processes, and that is the
    <option>--threads</option> flag. If this flag is used together with the
    <command>proc</command> move command with a PIDSPEC and if any of the
    task IDs in the PIDSPEC belongs to a thread in a process container, then
    <emphasis>all</emphasis> the sibling threads in that process container
    will also get moved. This flag provides an easy mechanism to move all
    threads of a process by simply specifying one thread in that process.
    The following example moves all threads running in cpuset
    <literal>three</literal> to cpuset <literal>two</literal> by using the
    <option>--threads</option> flag.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set two three
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
two          2 n          0 n       0     0    /two
three        3 n          0 n       10    0    /three


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s three
cset: "three" cpuset of CPUSPEC(3) with 10 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
&exampleuser;      16165     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16169     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16170     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16237     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16491     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16492     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      16493     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      17243     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      17244     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;      27133     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -p 16165 --threads -t two
cset: moving following pidspec: 16491,16493,16492,16170,16165,16169,27133,17244,17243,16237
cset: moving 10 userspace tasks to /two
[==================================================]%
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set two three
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
two          2 n          0 n       10    0    /two
three        3 n          0 n       0     0    /three</screen>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-move-taskset">
    <title>Moving all tasks from one cpuset to another</title>
    <para>
     There is a special case for moving all tasks currently running in one
     cpuset to another. This can be a common use case, and when you need to
     do it, specifying a PIDSPEC with <option>-p</option> is not necessary
     so long as you use the <option>-f/--fromset</option>
     <emphasis>and</emphasis> the <option>-t/--toset</option> options.
    </para>
    <para>
     The following example moves all 10 <literal>beagled</literal>
     threads back to cpuset <literal>three</literal> with this method.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l two three
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 10 tasks running
USER      PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
--------  ----- ----- ---- ---------
&exampleuser;       16165     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -…
&exampleuser;       16169     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       16170     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       16237     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       16491     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       16492     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       16493     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       17243     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       17244     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
&exampleuser;       27133     1 Soth beagled /usr/lib64/beagle/BeagleDaemon.exe --bg -...
cset: "three" cpuset of CPUSPEC(3) with 0 tasks running


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -f two -t three
cset: moving all tasks from two to /three
cset: moving 10 userspace tasks to /three
[==================================================]%
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set two three
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
two          2 n          0 n       0     0    /two
three        3 n          0 n       10    0    /three</screen>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-move-threads">
    <title>Moving kernel threads with <command>proc</command></title>
    <para>
     Kernel threads are special and <command>cset</command> detects tasks
     that are kernel threads and will refuse to move them unless you also
     add a <option>-k/--kthread</option> option to your
     <command>proc</command> move command. Even if you include
     <option>-k</option>, <command>cset</command> will still refuse to move
     the kernel thread if they are bound to specific CPUs. The reason for
     this is system protection.
    </para>
    <para>
     Several kernel threads, especially on the real-time Linux kernel,
     are bound to specific CPUs and depend on per-CPU kernel variables. If
     you move these threads to a different CPU than what they are bound to,
     you risk at best that the system will become horribly slow, and at
     worst a system hang. If you must move those threads (after all,
     <command>cset</command> needs to give the knowledgeable user access to
     the keys), then you also need to use the <option>--force</option>
     option.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Use <option>--force</option> with care</title>
     <para>
      Overriding a task move command with <option>--force</option> can have
      dire consequences for the system. Be sure of the command before you
      force it.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <para>
     The following example moves all unbound kernel threads running in
     the root cpuset to the cpuset named two by using the
     <option>-k</option> option.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -k -f root -t two
cset: moving all kernel threads from / to /two
cset: moving 70 kernel threads to: /two
cset: --&gt; not moving 76 threads (not unbound, use --force)
[==================================================]%
cset: done</screen>
    <para>
     This example uses the fromset→toset facility of the
     <command>proc</command> subcommand. However, it only specifies the
     <option>-k</option> option (not the <option>-m</option> option). This
     has the effect of moving all kernel threads only.
    </para>
    <para>
     Note that only 70 actual kernel threads were moved and 76 were not. The
     reason that 76 kernel threads were not moved was because they are bound
     to specific CPUs. Now, let us move those kernel threads back to
     <literal>root</literal>.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -k -f two -t root
cset: moving all kernel threads from /two to /
cset: ** no task matched move criteria
cset: **&gt; kernel tasks are bound, use --force if ok


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -s two
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
two          2 n          0 n       70    0    /two</screen>
    <para>
     <command>cset</command> refused to move the kernel threads back to
     <literal>root</literal> because it says that they are
     <quote>bound</quote>. Let us check this with the
     <command>taskset</command> command.
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -l -s two | head -5
cset: "two" cpuset of CPUSPEC(2) with 70 tasks running
USER     PID   PPID  SPPr TASK NAME
-------- ----- ----- ---- ---------
root         2     0 Soth [kthreadd]
root        55     2 Soth [khelper]


&prompt.user;<command>taskset</command> -p 2
pid 2's current affinity mask: 4


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -s two
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
two          2 n          0 n       70    0    /two</screen>
    <para>
     Of course, since the cpuset named <literal>two</literal> only has CPU2
     assigned to it, after it was moved the unbound kernel threads from
     <literal>root</literal> to <literal>two</literal>, their affinity masks
     got automatically changed to only use CPU2. This is evident from the
     <command>taskset</command> output which is a hex value. To really move
     these threads back to root, force the move as follows:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -k -f two -t root --force
cset: moving all kernel threads from /two to /
cset: moving 70 kernel threads to: /
[==================================================]%
cset: done</screen>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-destroy">
   <title>Destroying tasks</title>
   <para>
    There actually is no <command>cset</command> subcommand or option to
    destroy tasks—it is not really needed. Tasks exist and are accessible
    on the system as normal, even if they happen to be running in one cpuset
    or another. To destroy tasks, use the usual
    <keycombo><keycap function="control"/> <keycap>C</keycap></keycombo>
    method or by using the <command>kill(1)</command> command.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-shielding-set-proc">
  <title>Implementing shielding with <command>set</command> and <command>proc</command></title>

  <para>
   With the preceding material on the <command>set</command> and
   <command>proc</command> subcommands, you now have the background to
   implement the basic shielding model, like the <command>shield</command>
   subcommand.
  </para>

  <para>
   While <command>shield</command> provides this functionality already, doing
   this manually can still be useful. For example, to implement a shielding
   strategy that need more functionality than <command>shield</command> can
   provide. In such cases, you need to first
   stop using <command>shield</command> since that subcommand will interfere
   with the further application of <command>set</command> and
   <command>proc</command>. However, you will still need to implement the
   functionality of <command>shield</command> to implement
   successful shielding.
  </para>

  <para>
   Remember from the above sections describing <command>shield</command>,
   that shielding has at minimum three cpusets: <literal>root</literal>,
   which is always present and contains all CPUs; <literal>system</literal>
   which is the <emphasis>non-shielded</emphasis> set of CPUs and runs
   unimportant system tasks; and <literal>user</literal>, which is the
   <emphasis>shielded</emphasis> set of CPUs and runs your important tasks.
   Remember also that <command>shield</command> moves all movable tasks into
   <literal>system</literal> and, optionally, moves unbound kernel threads
   into <literal>system</literal> as well.
  </para>

  <para>
   You start first by creating the <literal>system</literal> and
   <literal>user</literal> cpusets as follows. Let us assume that the machine
   is a four-CPU machine without NUMA memory features. The system cpuset
   should hold only CPU0 while the user cpuset should hold the rest of the
   CPUs.
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 0 -s system
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "system"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1-3 -s user
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "user"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       333   2    /
user         1-3 n        0 n       0     0    /user
system       0 n          0 n       0     0    /system</screen>

  <para>
   Now, move all running user processes into the
   <literal>system</literal> cpuset:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -f root -t system
cset: moving all tasks from root to /system
cset: moving 188 userspace tasks to /system
[==================================================]%
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       146    2   /
user         1-3 n        0 n       0      0   /user
system       0 n          0 n       187    0   /system</screen>

  <para>
   This completes the basic shielding setup. Since all user space tasks are
   running in <literal>system</literal>, anything that is spawned from them
   will also run in <literal>system</literal>. The <literal>user</literal>
   cpuset has nothing running in it unless you put tasks there with the
   <command>proc</command> subcommand as described above. If you also want
   to move movable kernel threads from <literal>root</literal> to
   <literal>system</literal> (to achieve a form of <quote>interrupt
   shielding</quote> on a real time Linux kernel, for example), you would
   execute the following command as well:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -k -f root -t system
cset: moving all kernel threads from / to /system
cset: moving 70 kernel threads to: /system
cset: --&gt; not moving 76 threads (not unbound, use --force)
[==================================================]%
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       76    2    /
user         1-3 n        0 n       0     0    /user
system       0 n          0 n       257   0    /system</screen>

  <para>
   At this point, you have achieved the simple shielding model that the
   <command>shield</command> subcommand provides. You can now add other
   cpuset definitions to expand your shielding strategy beyond that simple
   model.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sec-shielding-cpuset-hierarchy-set-proc">
  <title>Implementing hierarchy with set and proc</title>

  <para>
   One popular extended <emphasis>shielding</emphasis> model is based on
   hierarchical cpusets, each with diminishing numbers of CPUs. This model
   is used to create <emphasis>priority cpusets</emphasis> that allow
   assignment of CPU resources to tasks based on some arbitrary priority
   definition. The idea is that a higher priority task will get access to
   more CPU resources than a lower priority task.
  </para>

  <para>
   The example provided here once again assumes a machine with four CPUs and
   no NUMA memory features. This base serves to illustrate the point well;
   however, note that if your machine has (many) more CPUs, then strategies
   such as this and others get more interesting.
  </para>

  <para>
   Define a shielding setup as in the previous section where there is a
   <literal>system</literal> cpuset with only CPU0 that takes care of
   <quote>unimportant</quote> system tasks. You will usually require this
   type of cpuset since it forms the basis of shielding. Modify the
   strategy to not use a <literal>user</literal> cpuset&mdash;instead create
   several new cpusets each holding one more CPU than the other. These
   cpusets will be called <literal>prio_low</literal> with one CPU,
   <literal>prio_med</literal> with two CPUs, <literal>prio_high</literal>
   with three CPUs, and <literal>prio_all</literal> with all CPUs.
  </para>

  <note>
   <title>The sense behind creating a prio_all cpuset with all CPUs</title>
   <para>
    You may ask, why create a <literal>prio_all</literal> with all CPUs when
    that is substantially the definition of the <literal>root</literal>
    cpuset? The answer is that it is best to keep a separation between the
    <literal>root</literal> cpuset and everything else, even if a particular
    cpuset duplicates <literal>root</literal> exactly. Usually, automation
    is build on top of a cpuset strategy. In these cases, it is best to
    avoid using invariant names of cpusets, such as <literal>root</literal>
    for example, in this automation.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   All of these <literal>prio_*</literal> cpusets can be created under root,
   in a flat way; however, it is advantageous to create them as a hierarchy.
   The reasoning for this is twofold: first, if a cpuset is destroyed, all
   its tasks are moved to its parent; second, one can use exclusive CPUs in
   a hierarchy.
  </para>

  <!-- libor: "Burden" does not seem to collocate with "simplify"
   Anyway, I propose to leave out mentions about plans as I consider them
   inappropriate in product documentation. The whole paragraph should be
   left out.
  <para>
   There is a planned addition to the <command>proc</command> subcommand
   that will allow moving a specified PIDSPEC of tasks running in a
   specified cpuset to its parent. This addition will simplify the automation
   burden.
  </para>-->

  <para>
   If a cpuset has CPUs that are exclusive to it, then other cpusets may not
   use those CPUs unless they are children of that cpuset. This has
   more relevance to machines with many CPUs and more complex strategies.
  </para>

  <para>
   Start with a clean slate and build the appropriate cpusets as follows:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -r
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       344   0    /


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 0-3 prio_all
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "prio_all"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 1-3 /prio_all/prio_high
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "/prio_all/prio_high"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 2-3 /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "/prio_all/prio_high/prio_med"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 3 /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med/prio_low
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "/prio_all/prio_high/prio_med/prio_low"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -c 0 system
cset: --&gt; created cpuset "system"


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -r
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       344   2    /
system       0 n          0 n       0     0    /system
prio_all     0-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all
prio_high    1-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high
prio_med     2-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med
prio_low     3 n          0 n       0     0    /prio_all/pr...rio_med/prio_low</screen>

  <note>
   <title>Why <option>-r/--recurse</option> is needed in this case</title>
   <para>
    The option <option>-r</option>/<option>--recurse</option> lists all the
    sets in the last command above. If you execute that command without
    <option>-r/--recurse</option>, <literal>prio_med</literal> and
    <literal>prio_low</literal> cpusets would not appear.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   The strategy is now implemented. This means that you can move all user space
   tasks and all movable kernel threads into the <literal>system</literal>
   cpuset to activate the shield.
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> proc -m -k -f root -t system
cset: moving all tasks from root to /system
cset: moving 198 userspace tasks to /system
cset: moving 70 kernel threads to: /system
cset: --&gt; not moving 76 threads (not unbound, use --force)
[==================================================]%
cset: done


&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -r
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       76    2    /
system       0 n          0 n       268   0    /system
prio_all     0-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all
prio_high    1-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high
prio_med     2-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med
prio_low     3 n          0 n       0     0    /prio_all/pr...rio_med/prio_low</screen>

  <para>
   The shield is now active. Since the <literal>prio_*</literal> cpuset
   names are unique, you can assign tasks to them either via their simple
   name, or their full path (as described in
   <xref linkend="sec-shielding-cpuset-proc-exec"/>).
  </para>

  <para>
   You may have noted that there is an ellipsis in the path of the
   <literal>prio_low</literal> cpuset in the listing above. This is done
   to fit the output onto an 80 character screen. To see
   the entire line, use the <option>-v</option>/<option>--verbose</option>
   flag as follows:
  </para>

<screen>&prompt.user;<command>cset</command> set -l -r -v
cset:
Name         CPUs-X       MEMs-X    Tasks Subs Path
------------ ---------- - ------- - ----- ---- ----------
root         0-3 y        0 y       76    2    /
system       0 n          0 n       268   0    /system
prio_all     0-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all
prio_high    1-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high
prio_med     2-3 n        0 n       0     1    /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med
prio_low     3 n          0 n       0     0    /prio_all/prio_high/prio_med/prio_low</screen>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
